[Music]
all right hello everyone welcome to
actinflab
livestream number 39.2 it's march 9th
welcome to the actin flap we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links here on the slide
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve on our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
check out
activeinference.org to learn more about
anything that the lab is up to
today in
stream number 39.2 we're in our third
discussion around this paper
morphogenesis as bayesian inference a
variational approach to pattern
formation control in complex biological
systems
by franz kuchling who's here with us as
well as fristen gyorgev and levin
so
we're gonna have a fun discussion in the
dot two the dot zero was some background
and context hopefully overviewing the
paper
the dot one we had a discussion that
opened up several threads
and today we will in the dot two
say hello
on the introductions and then just jump
in
to a blank slide or to a not blank slide
so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and i'll pass it to dean
good morning i'm dean i'm in calgary and
i am going to say that i have one thing
i want to look at down the road which is
how long is a person a stem cell
which i think this paper might help us
parse a little bit and i'll pass it down
to blue
hi i'm blue i'm a researcher in new
mexico and i also
similar to dean have questions about um
when a cell becomes a cancer cell and
like how does it develop its own
generative model and just in general
like when you're looking at complex
systems how these small perturbations
can lead to like a totally different
effect downstream which i think is kind
of related to the stem cell question
that dean has
and i'll pass it over to the first
author events
hi i'm france um
i am a phd student in the 11th lab in
tufts
near boston and yeah i study
part of active influence in my
theoretical work and i do a lot of
experimental work as well looking at
information processing and organisms and
cells
oh so where does
stemness
or how do stem cells play into this
paper and this line of research france
definitely something we've touched on
but just to kind of start generally and
then we'll zoom in somewhere so take it
away
sure um
the the idea is that the
the cells initially when they're in the
simulation when they're being
initialized they have um the random
emulation initialized and they have very
low
beliefs about what cell type they are
they can be one of four different cell
types in this particular simulation
and they all share
a a model a
morphology they could achieve that they
essentially are programmed to achieve at
some point
but none of the cells are any of the
given cell types initially at least not
with any um significant precision
um
and as they move along signaling to each
other and sensing each other and
secreting
signal types in response to each other
they then slowly by slowly infer a cell
type which essentially is
differentiation
so
cells starting with low precision about
what kind of cell they believe
themselves to be
and then there's a process of
differentiation
so dean or blue any
thoughts on that sort of stem to
differentiated
uh continuum and i'll pull up an image
from a non-active perspective that also
shows that kind of a continuum
so
i
have just something to add that's ties
into the paper where there's aberrant
signaling so
a stem cell differentiates but then
during the process of carcinogenesis
like retains some kind of or or d
differentiates into something that's
more similar to
a stem cell than it is to a different
kind of cell
and so this plasticity is important to
retain like so that we can repair
ourselves but also it can lead to
kind of a
an aberrant signaling pattern
yep like this uh
notion of having a terminal cell
revert to a state
and regain the ability of having
stemness is
one of the characteristics of cancer
because it can then sometimes
differentiate into other cell types that
are like normal and downstream of a
precursor or abnormal in some other way
how is also something
i was going to say it's not something
that happens and especially in higher
organisms right not not every organisms
keeps absolute stem cells in all kinds
of populations one example that i used
to work on is an uh and zebra fish where
you have
an always developing eye and there's
certain
um
they're parts of the retina essentially
that can be differentiate some extents
they're not entirely stem cells they
have a stem cell niche as well but
there's also especially they know also
in higher organisms while they keep
those populations of either stem cells
or of um already partially
differentiated cells that can be
differentiate so it's an important um
part regeneration um
and ironically this is something that's
not been studied for 401 of this there's
some older research that was done where
a highly highly regenerative organisms
when they undergo um they did this in
salamanders and they injected them with
carcinogens and they basically had it
um you know saw a tumor progressing and
then they cut up a lymph in these
elements of highly regenerating it would
actually renormalize um the the tumors
essentially so initiation of
regeneration and those organisms seems
to actually counteract
um
cancer progression and even kind of
remove the tumors
which is very interesting and it kind of
this feeds a little bit into the idea in
this paper as well that
regeneration right what what happens is
you suddenly now have a much higher flow
of information on things to rearrange to
to redifferentiate
and
and that is kind of like what i was
thinking as well with the simulation
here of the the the cancer rescue
phenomena where you
you get you rescue this um this
formation of aberrancy abram cells and
iron signaling by having a strong
contact um between cells
as well nothing i'm modeling generation
here although you can i think in the
original paper carl has done some way to
cut i think part off and let it let it
grow again i think that has been done in
the original paper and knowing one's
place
um
but that's something to kind of keep in
mind this is something that that
is experimentally highly studied
um to an extent
so one general note and then a question
this question this idea that the
organisms that have the highly
regenerative capacity and there's a
continuum from regrowing just the tail
to regrowing a whole limb to
kind of an extreme or a highly um
regenerative case like the planaria that
was studied in this paper so it's all
kind of on a continuum from total
ability to regenerate from any adult
somatic cell can fully recapitulate the
full population
all the way to a total opposite of that
and then
you pointed out that it might be related
to
cancer
progressions and phenotype and that
speaks to what blue brought up about the
um
[Music]
like
system level effects there's the
individual cell and there's the system
level because clearly there's something
about the
system level in the regenerative
situation that would lead to this being
different
or maybe it could be explained by just
something
internal to the model anyways um
you mentioned that higher information
was associated with rearrangement
could you explain a little bit about
that or how does it play out in this
paper or in general
yeah it's basically the um the idea that
and it's not not so much the the total
information content but the flow of it
and we talked a little bit about this
last time right it's hard to really
kind of quantify this in a in a more
meaningful biological sense but the idea
is that
it's it's information flow like i think
um dean asks a question like i said is
more information always good and my kind
of answer to that was
it's it's it's within context of what
the
what the participating autism can
receive and can process so
in the sense that if you have
you know cells that you know is
processing certain information with a
certain kind of rates time constants
then
kind of getting information in within
with that time frame in mind is what
what makes it
more likely for them to kind of
understand better their environment
and react to it as opposed to a cell you
kind of think of it also cancer cells
um that you know have the whole sensory
part completely perturbed that do not
react to the environment anymore
then
everything else becomes noise and it
gets ignored um
that's kind of the idea so there is
there is a lot of different differences
in of how the cancer cells because they
have changed ion profile iron channel
profiles have changed uh machinery of
what they're actually transcribing so
all of that leads to the difference in
how signals are being processed
and understanding that and then reacting
to that is i think is a key to to
understand and
treating this disease
awesome thanks dean
i don't know if i have the answer to my
my question um which which is how long
is a person a
a in finger and scare quotes a stem cell
but
one of the things you mentioned bronze
in the
point one was
i think steven asked the question about
how much volume or in the flow and what
i've heard you say back was um
it's always a state space dependency
which which i
when i'm reading the paper was i think
you made a really good sound
um case for that but then one of the
things that when you had to when you had
to
sign off
one of the questions that i brought up
hopefully that maybe we can discuss a
little bit today is like in figure four
and five
um
of the paper
all that black area around when the
sort of cells
move into into place and that's a crude
way of describing what's going on there
but all that black area around that
am i
is it fair to say that that's kind of
the
the state space dependency or is that
just assumed and how would we because
daniel did a good job of sort of saying
there's some invisibility aspects to
this when we mult do multiple layering
and so
how how do you give people a sense of
what's going on in that
in that black that blacked out area
right i think i think black is a good
a good color representation because it's
not really a color i don't think but it
but it kind of speaks to
this idea that um
we've got these low beliefs but how long
for how long as a person or as cells as
a cluster of cells is that beneficial
right when we're talking we're talking
of course here on under the the big
umbrella of morphology so that was kind
of where i was wondering today maybe you
could
you could explain it because you the
focus the eye tends to focus on the
object within the frame
as opposed to sort of the area around
the what we would consider to be the
object so
maybe you can kind of help me understand
this state state-space dependency piece
yeah i mean so
um if if you have a look at figure two
so and um what i didn't plot in the in
the in the figure four and five and two
i did is the backup concentrations right
so there are of course some
some levels of cons of signaling uh
molecules in the background as well um
which will also of course be the case in
the in the actual simulations um down
the line four and five
um the
the blackness so the one interesting
part about this simulation which was
done mainly for
simplicity and lack of necessity
is to not actually have an external
environment per se like there's nothing
right there's no external force like
outside of base everything in the
simulations is done by the cells where
the cells they make the environment
right so essentially there's an external
environment by the signaling molecules
that they put out but we don't have any
external um limited like limits around
it we just basically that's the space we
plot um
the signaling molecules don't go farther
than that um and there isn't any
external force um
which we could do right we
the power simulations we do this
asymmetry we essentially get uh
we get sort of an implicit environment
by changing the response to the signals
around each other you can imagine that
you put something in the medium that
that flips how how old signaling is
being processed and that's it
um so
back to your question so this about this
blackness um
and when is that beneficial if i said
that question correctly it's
there is of course like a hype like a
precision component to it and kind of
more
less hand less hand wavy if uh you know
if your environment is very volatile
and constantly changes and you keep
right you have a not not this
essentially it's a closed system right
if you had an open system right you
constantly would get signals also from
the environment this will also become
all a lot messier and especially
initially
right in the in the first frames of that
figure um four and five where we get the
simulations they all start together i
mentioned last time there are certain
smoothness requirements where like if we
had to put this dampening on the
sensitivity a long time so inverse
dampening it will get more sensitive
with time but just because initially
they're very unstructured they have you
know very low prior beliefs and they
will jump crazy if they have high
sensitive to each other because they're
in such close proximity
and um that is something that we of
course do see in biology right we do be
most um
especially the higher organisms right
they start often usually in close
environments now of course you can you
can argue this you don't need to go to
any information stuff you can argue well
it's just you know thermally insulated
they have their own food supplies it
makes you know just makes like a more
safe zone like just physically energy
speaking but i do think there's a big
component to it it's like shutting this
highly
volatile you know
it's self-inferring
organism off from influence to an
environment at a stage
when all these cells are figuring out
what to do each other so they need they
kind of need to have
a kind of a barrier between
signals from the environments which
normally you know to us adults between a
mature organism are not really dangerous
by 2n
developing organism full of stem cells
can be problematic and will basically
would um
perturb its natural kind of progression
in this states based on this sulfate
acquisition
there is a cool paper i can reference to
you from chris fields who i am from
disclosure i'm working with and very
much admire him
who wrote my paper about
motor solarity as exactly
the consequence of what i'm talking what
i just said the multicellularity
basically emerging in a as a way to
shut some cells or you know cells that
are
in an initial region of motility it's
also undergoing an evolution towards
complexity
needing some kind of barrier from the
environment basically making themselves
making creating a market bank around
them
that makes it so they're not constantly
you know being perturbed by the
environment and that's the idea of of
how my motorcycle to emotion in the
first place is to insulate
niches which will become stem cell
natures
from the environment so that
cells that are undergoing
you know very much very dynamic changes
in short amount of time
um that therefore need to be kind of
sensitive to the environment cannot be
need to be isolated from influence from
the environment that would perturb this
careful um inference of cell
type thanks dean
yeah so in this in this figure too you
can see that there's
we're talking about ranges because we've
got values
on the horizontal and the vertical
um
sides of the box
so
so one of the things that i think is
really interesting is that once you
so
you
we've all spelled it out if we're
dealing with active inference we want to
avoid something surprising right the
whole
the whole uh variational aspect of this
so
again if we're talking about going from
something that is has low beliefs to
something that
gains in in i'll say gains and
sensitivity
without hopefully killing
what i want to say next
if
if it's about signal adaptation to these
top-down conditions which
influence the final form taken
is there some way based on what you
researched with this paper is there some
way to know as you're approaching
that place of energy exhaustion like is
there something that the cell tells you
that it's it's finding this too
surprising because
one of the things we again we talked
about was that rate of change being so
rapid say like the u.n report on global
warming where we simply don't have the
machinery to be able to adapt is there
something that you found out through
this paper that kind of said to you
as you were looking at these things
oh wait a second here we're just gonna
we're gonna we're not our intent is not
to kill this thing off
but we're approaching that place where
the environment is just too
changing too fast
yeah i'm
trying to give you a more detangling
hand waviness but um let's start with
the general answer first so
um yes you do it's you can of course you
can like one way you can quickly see it
isn't that kind of like something that
you get with the picture and error plot
um that you all skip with the free
energy plot if you
um right in a perfect world you will get
like a nice move like you know
exponential decay of the free energy
function um if that keeps changing
bouncing up and down
um that will be very problematic i i did
some simulations afterward to not
include in this paper but based on
exactly the same stuff
um where i was including a time ver um
based on top of this time sensitivity um
you know increase so um that i use for
basically you know i'm increasing the
sensitivity
over the time but having a low in the
beginning on top of that i put in a an
impulsive like a sinusoidal or
a rectangular function which was um we
were just trying to simulate what i'm
doing in my in my experiments in a lab
where basically you know pulse certain
signaling
inputs to my organisms i wanted to see
basically if i randomized that or made
that in a certain certain pattern how
well would the simulation still be able
to cope with that and uh and
in the case where i had like a nice
regular pattern of that um you in the in
the free energy lan and the free energy
decay you hardly saw that
you know initially like initially even
minute since it was very high it was you
know you couldn't see it there there was
like a big jumpiness and fuzziness you
could see it also in the in the belief
updates uh you know
basically they were
um they kind of
emerged kind of like um they diverged
initially very strongly and that
diverged in terms of their beliefs
um that they had about themselves but
then kind of afterwards the um when the
sensitivity overall was kind of
um acclimating but was kind of varying
around this acclimation point
you didn't see that much anymore in the
um
in the in the in the regular pattern but
when the ones were less regular
um that was very much perturbed and the
and the fan energy also didn't actually
quite
uh did not only did it not um
come to kind of like uh to this
asymptotic behavior but it actually
started increasing again basically um
just was really perturbed and you didn't
see that so john's a question like um
how do you see
if if you are
not adapting correctly
even though you don't actually know yet
what the what your external status i
would answer it's
how much are you switching back and
forth between your beliefs
and uh
i guess more precisely also like how
certain are you of that right this is
something that we talk about in medical
immersion which i've recently from the
last people i've been getting into and
reading about metacognition and rats and
primates and other animals saying the
first step to metacognition is
as far as i understand it is
having a certain confidence about your
results with rats where they basically
gave rats the option in this kind of
cognitive task
um that they could also just not answer
the task not to not not push the level
because i think it was leverage um i
think what the task was but it was based
levers and they had an option to not
push a lever
for which they will get a lower reward
than if they um
a much lower award than if they got it
correctly but more than if they got it
wrongly and so what they saw is that
they actually would in certain certain
cases when you know when they hadn't
learned it when they hadn't learned the
task correctly they would just not push
the lever
and that is used as like a first
instance off of the medical cognition a
sense of they
must have been unsure about what you do
and then chose not to do it
so
i think that's kind of like if you
it's one thing if you kind of lean back
and forth because you always think well
you know i'm this and that
um
being unsure is normal but kind of uh
kind of uh constantly going back and
forth between certain states of
shortness is also problematic
so that's the generalized answer to this
um
yeah i think
i think the interesting thing there is
the emphasis on the back and forth
metaphorically speaking we tend to uh
give a lot of attention over to the
balance piece but what what you're
talking about when you're talking about
the environment is not the plank as much
as a moving fulcrum so how do you how do
you adjust
right
the balance i guess is the is the
outcome but it's the uh the process
itself is
the back and forth so
yeah i i wondered about that because
some things you do want and from like
from an epigenetic standpoint
you do want certain cells to die you
want their energy to expire
absolutely
right that's part of the back and forth
as opposed to the balance you know
there's no balance metaphor you want
there you want them to die yeah and
they're not dying so that's really
interesting thank you
now i wanted to add one one more kind of
attempt to answer more specifically is
there's a paper by uh i'm probably
pronouncing this name wrong drawfully
which was um
just google valence and uh active
inference
um they basically looked at you know
valence in terms of like um judging if
your actions are you know certain like
are they
better or worse basically is that
um are you you'd be assigning a a sign
positive or negative two to outcomes
um and they were doing that uh in the
active infant schemes and they were
defining it and you know there's other
definitions i'm not everyone was going
to be about this but they were looking
at it in an infant scheme about the rate
of change they were looking at the first
and second order derivatives
um of um how
i'm saying this correctly um
about how the
prior beliefs were updated to the
position that how how important like how
how sure they were about what cell type
there were and so basically in the
segment order derivative basically how
much would they change at any given time
in their beliefs
that's what they um what they plugged in
valence into different mode it gets more
complex than that but that's the gist of
it
so um that i think is a
in the within the frame of active
inference is a more specific answer your
question is
look at the the rate of change by which
your beliefs are
updating
and that with respect to your
uncertainty of course um there's this
whole
um cause i've written about this as well
um i'm very interested as well from the
browse standpoint of you is that stress
stress sensing mechanisms like stress is
a universal um driver
um in biology it's actually much more
important than rewards i kind of find
that we are talking about rewards but um
biology is much more focused on on
stress
um because it's more informative and
it's more important to deal with than
than what maximizing but of course you
always say it's just a negative but
the the point that being is
uh stress as in terms of for uncertainty
like not having not minimizing your
energy effectively and stably
um that will lead to stress and there's
paper that doesn't humans i think i
mentioned the last time as well what
they do experiments with humans
and mice as well were they
very ethical where they shocked um they
give the electric shocks i think they're
both mice and humans
um and then they showed that the
level so they were more stressed out not
just by this like the sharks themselves
but they couldn't predict
um the electric shocks so it's that
uncertainty of what coming next i think
that is the most
if i had to like say one thing that is
most negative of uh of you're going in a
bad place
so if you are stressed because you have
no idea what's happening and you cannot
even if you know something that's going
to happen you know when it's happening
that's a lot less bad than if you don't
know at all
um one last really dark example to
really make this a dark place is there
is a i'm from um i was born east germany
um
i guess i was only when you open the
wall fell so um but we you know my
parents were very much and
there was uh this um now it's a museum
but it was a prison
for the the basically political
detainees in east germany and east
berlin
and we went there as a class once and um
they showed us all the things all the
techniques they used to interrogate
um prisoners including torture and one
of the torture devices
um was i believe a japanese device where
you would
get you put your head down on
this device and there's a
water that's dropping from the top onto
your neck
so you think at this point like uh it
doesn't sound too bad right the problem
was is that the drops you know there's
um
there's a lot of viscosity in there so
um you know a lot of kind of
fluctuations so the drops wouldn't
always come at the same time and it kept
repeating repelling um happening over
time and time again so what the and the
prisoners actually people that used to
be in prison they were actually one was
giving the tour
so they were telling us yeah if you
under the device after a couple hours or
so these drops will feel like hammers on
your on your neck
and apparently a big component of that
was the um
not the the body not being able to adapt
to it because you know the drops don't
come at a perfect five second interval
it happens kind of at some fast
randomized um intervals
so um
that i think there's a huge part in and
not just looking at stress over time but
how
you can adapt that stress and in order
to adapt to stress adaptation to me
always involves a component of
prediction if you can't predict the
source of the stress when it happens
it makes things a lot worse this has
been shown extensively in humans and
also in
in lower organisms
and i believe um very strongly that
there's something fundamental to any
biological system to fundamental drive
if you if you view if you
you describe to the point of view that
um minimizing uncertainty in the
environment is a fundamental drive of
life
then
with that you prescribe that minimizing
stress and the source of stress over
time and being able to predict it is
also fundamental and lacto of makes a
very dangerous system
blue thanks
so all that's super interesting um just
okay so let me i'm going to start at the
front and work backwards so in terms of
uncertainty and um
how that's what causes stress
uh i'm really kind of i don't know
reluctant to use the word stress in a
biological system like i think about
stressing a biological system is like
pushing it out of equilibrium um
but but maybe that's just a stimulus
right like i want you to rebalance and
go to like a new equilibrium like or
like turn on heat shock protein or you
know there's a variety of different
things like many ways you can view
stress as a stimulus to do something new
or to perturb the system in a new way um
but but in terms of uncertainty i think
that there's a lot of truth in
um
how uncomfortable
people are with uncertainty like at a
cognitive level and you can even see it
like in the stock market before like the
election is in before the election
results like the stock market goes crazy
and because nobody knows i mean it's not
that one candidate is preferable over
the other but it's just the unknowing is
very
um
like
people freak out
so so and that speaks i think to
metacognition
also um
and then so i i wanted to back up a
little bit if i can
um to your discussion of information
flow
and how that might be difficult to
quantify and daniel i don't know can you
flip to the section for me please on um
the generalized flow section i think we
started to get into that a little bit
last week and
we did discuss it in the dot zero but i
have like i i know that this is very um
mathematically technical and so i just
have a little bit of of questions about
um this and maybe
you can help explain it in a way that's
perhaps less technical but specifically
information flow and chris fields is
coming uh to discuss the fep for generic
quantum systems next week and so i can i
can similarly interrogate him about
about some of this stuff uh and i'm
looking forward to it but um
you know we have a discussion there's a
discussion in the paper about the
probability flow
um
and
information like a probability current i
think is actually what is used and
getting into
information currents like if you look up
what is an information current i think
um there's like the idea of the von
neumann information current and um that
like is explicitly related to quantum
systems so is there any similar like do
we have a way to measure information
current because even when mike came to
the live stream and talked about um
um expanding cognition biological
cognition computational boundary of
itself there was sorry um but when you
expand biological cognition like there's
you know you're basically expanding your
informational awareness and so is there
anything like an information current or
how can you best relate that within a
biological system is it like an
expansion of your computational boundary
or does it look like just more
information goes in and comes out
i think it's
uh it depends on what
depends on what level you're looking at
i would say it's both um so
the the the second part you mentioned
that the information flow comes in and
out that's something we just have more
access to biologically speaking
experimentally right
um
and you can absolutely you know you can
you can look at you know you have all
these
uh sensors for for for sensors for
receptors being activated for
um
genetic um transcription
in response to that so so that's
something that we can you have the best
chance of quantifying experimentally
and in terms of computationally it's
something you can monitor and then also
couple that with what chris fields um
good thing you mentioned that because
then i can relate to him that's
basically what he's also very interested
in right like how how does physical
energy of course played all all into
this with the mid and embarrassing
metabolism right now this comes for free
that's something that biologists often
kind of um not broad it's actually no
theoretical we're all just often kept
under under the table because the idea
is that energy is abundant and uh and in
in life which is to extend true right
there's plenty of sunlight there's
plenty of things to spend food around
um but at the same time
locally just with entropy
there is a strong competition there so
just because you are living in a
reservoir that has plenty of food and
sunlight that doesn't mean that you
locally are gonna gonna survive because
of people locally competing with you the
same is true right i mean uh this is
always like when you talk to
um when you talk to people that people
that you know have
problems the idea of um
what why does entropy i don't want to
say names but if you
that's saying that entropy is always
increased if chaos in the universe
increases how do we see
much more structure evolving and then um
the of course the answer to that is that
well just like in a path of water if you
have certain oil droplets are going to
come together because overall that makes
that gives more degrees of freedom for
all the water molecules so the entire
entire system entropy did increase but
you managed to find a
solution that does increase that by
locally creating more order that's the
drive of um
i think of life overall the quote that
probably the talk that got me into
biology is was from a biophysicist in
heidelberg was saying life is not about
energy it's for entropy
um
but
the two come together right yes it's
about how much information is available
but then by extent of that once you are
subscribed to that once you have to form
these localized structures then energy
becomes important again
um so and that's what i think is needed
right now when you have this high view
highly spatially organized systems
energy suddenly does become
something that is valuable again
um
yeah i think i kind of lost my train of
thought there
um the
the boundary yourself that's right your
the other information flow that was the
part about information but we can
measure that um we have good ideas what
was what's lacking is
and uh quantum understanding of of
how metabolism is really hooked into the
information flow
whether or not it's built into the model
or whether it's ad hoc just down down
the line you give it certain resources
after a while it just exploits them the
boundary itself is interesting because
and of course in the cell we think well
we have a you know there's a membrane
the boundary of itself is very fairly
obvious
it's not as easy as that i think and of
course if you look at two multicellular
organisms it becomes um you know a
tissue scale then that becomes a lot
more difficult but even on a cellular
level
if you have certain receptors um you
know you have certain activations of it
then
a modern energy generator of general
monologues in the active inference
scheme but especially an iterative
stream you also have a model of yourself
right and if
at what point
your own your own what you're what
you're secreting your own your signals
that you secrete also feedback into what
you're sensing after all
so it is kind of thought that that that
whole system is very much perturbed in
cancer cells as well where
the
how much like is it is are you actually
receiving things from the environment
are you basically just
uh secreting and secreting and you don't
really react to it anymore
so the the boundary of self what what
mike might already talked about this
here will be have been much more than i
can be about this but the idea is
the boundary itself is encoded
specifically with time and spatial
constraints so like how much you're
burning yourself what you want yourself
might be more general about this
yourself model depends
very much on your sensual or your
sensory
memory like how how far do you sense and
how and spatially how how much water can
you sense and how much back do you have
encoded as memory how much are effects
in the past um um persisting so that you
know so even though if you have a cell
there's a certain membrane
if if that cell does not actually keep
any track if that cell is not somehow a
sensing or beyond a certain boundary and
then it creates on boundary by these
highly peripheral cells that are
basically surrounding themselves with
each other then suddenly the environment
becomes mute um so the boundary of the
self has essentially expanded i would
argue
um
i think that's kind of the the thought
train here i
i'm just hope that was some way i would
answer the question
awesome blue
so um just i was curious um you
mentioned that there was a talk that um
got you hooked into biology was it eric
smith and his discussion of biology and
entropy because that's also fabulous
it was not i'm real just saying that was
um
damn that's really embarrassing that the
guy i don't remember right now the name
of the person that got me into biologies
ugh it's as i speak english right now
it's all in german back then and always
kind of my brain then has problems
switching between those two and content
as well as language um it'll come back
to me
probably within this talk
eric smith does a wonderful job though
of um you know discussing biology in
terms of entropy and so if you are not
familiar with this work i would just
highly recommend it yeah
that really
reflects on our um discussion what parts
of the self model are important to carry
forward
and then what are the affordances for
direct and indirect
self-modification
so that's one
piece like you mentioned the autocrine
signaling and that's not even a
contentious component it just is being
modeled in a different way with active
inference rather than just a molecular
event that's happening that like cells
secrete molecules that they also possess
receptors
to measure it's just putting that into a
framework of reflexive self-modeling and
stigmargy and niche modification here
but just one other point that i thought
was really
maybe useful to highlight was this
sensitivity and just like many of the
terms in actin for kind of seeing that
there is a
narrow or a quantitative sense and then
there's a broader sense because in any
dynamical systems model you might hear
about
sensitivity of the parameter which is
how much changing that parameter changes
the outcome of the system
and so that's a quantitative sense
and then also
it was brought up that it's important to
model these like second order
derivatives like how fast are things
changing relative to expectations or how
fast are they changing how they're
changing
and
that is what the generalized flow is
it's all those higher derivatives
so
we can use that quantitative sense of
sensitivity to look at how parameter
changes in the generalized coordinates
of motion matter
but also we can
perhaps with cognitive modeling
take this discussion of sensitivity in
the way that people are usually meaning
it
like sensitivity of what is seen on
someone's emotional state
and then model that using cognitive
parameters
like valence and affect
even though that's
quite a disjoint use from the parameter
sensitivity
discussion on the generalized
coordinates
so
it's was an awesome discussion with like
what is stress
and how does that relate to the
parametric sort of neutral perspective
on what stress or sensitivity what might
mean
just the model descriptive
versus some of these
functional
or
um phenomenological even
ways that these terms come into play
blue
so that's super interesting thinking
about uh sensitivity and
stress in just in terms of cognition
right like so i know like people that
have sensory processing disorders get
like super aggravated by something like
a bright light or like a windy day
um and just how how sensitivity does
play into maybe the flow of of
information like
because you know i'm suddenly sensitive
to this then i'm also sensitized to
every other thing in my environment like
someone's screaming over here and it's
windy and it's hot and it's bright and
then like i become just so over
stimulated right like people have these
these processing things and
it's sensory
is that something that like has momentum
right like so you have enhanced
sensitivity and does that just like then
all of a sudden you're just you're so
sensitive like we hear people say stuff
like that like stop being so sensitive
um just in terms of cognitive processing
i thought that that was um
just super interesting
i think that's an excellent point i mean
that's that's something that that that
shows exactly how important it is for
humans right you're gonna argue low
levels as well um and in the evolution
to be able to model our sensitive
actually change our sensitivity right we
would never be able to have
conversations in our environments if we
couldn't change
consciously our
and sometimes subconsciously as well
our sensitivity parameters and um
i think
that's something also then also feeds
into metacognition right you learn like
oh well um i'm not paying attention
enough so something to pay more
attention to uh
you're trying to tune this in and i
think that's
the
in the sense of on the cellular level i
think what where that feeds in is
the
is by learning over time right by how
much being how many receptors are being
activated how does that defeat in
downstream then there is this component
where essentially the the cell can upper
sensitivity by expressing more receptors
by if though if it's not understanding
it's it's uh it's inputs it can increase
those proteins they're responsible for
sensing these things
um and there's also different if you
talk about ion channels specifically
that we work with that there are
different versions of iron channels that
have different rate constants
um the same is true for other um
uh for for active proteins as well such
as pumps so that becomes an a lot more
you know explicitly
um modulating sensitivity over time
in a way to um to you know better react
and cope with uh adapt to its
environment again adaptation keep in
mind involves prediction in most cases
if not explicitly then basically
awesome and by the way um then the guy
is michael houseman and heidelberg
before i turn around my grave
oh that was the person coming to physics
to biology biophysics
cool
um
just to kind of connect that change in
sensitivity to some of those mechanisms
so
if it's the sensitivity to a given
hormone or a given circulating molecule
then that sometimes gets accomplished
biologically by changes in like the
membrane receptor density or changes in
downstream signaling pathways so even if
the amount of receptor in the membrane
stays constant it's like you can release
more of the neurotransmitter in the
synapse or you could have more or less
receptors or you could have more or less
of all these regulators and
phosphorylating proteins etc in the
downstream signaling pathways because
there's a
lot of complexity in that space but
there's a lot of knobs including rates
of change in rates of rates of change
and lag effects with transcription
factors
and all this other
basically any
thing is possible
and then at the organism level just to
give one and then anyone else maybe at
the some other level like
it's kind of like
a nest may ant being sensitive to
interactions
and then a nurse
who's a younger aunt is like initially
more susceptible or more sensitive
due to multiple reasons like at the
antenna at the brain
in just spatially where the nurse is and
then there's this
um
development towards being a forager
being sensitive to forage or cues
finding oneself in spaces where there
are forage or cues that are useful
so there's a lot of ways that these
changes in the type
of sensitivity
again are already things that we talk
about
in developmental biology
and so it's so cool to see how that is
connected to the molecular mechanism
the affective angle
and then
with the underpinning of the generalized
flow
yeah
so you guys can push push back on this
heart if you want but it's interesting i
one of the
terms that i coined was that stress
programming or at least programming
with stress
assumed was basically learning either
formally or informally
that's what it is because there's a
certain amount of stress involved be it
positive or
negative but i kind of
threw that through that
viewfinder i think it's interesting that
back to the back and forth thing
stress programming can be safer
or it can be riskier
and you know as long as it's not sort of
killing the learner
if safer in the sense of
as intervention
i think this paper
showed that you can intervene
but riskier is as distribution like
sending something
out into the unknown it can be safer as
teaching
or taught
it can also be riskier as i'm teaching
or untaught
sort of just sort of throwing somebody
into a situation
and see whether they can paddle
or not
the last thing is it can also be seen as
both modeling in the safer sense because
we've
reduced some of the variation
or it can also be riskier as in terms of
coordinating
meaning the person has to kind of figure
it out as they're flying the plane
so
i wonder what you guys think do you
think that
can we is there some agreement that
learning in general
be it formalized or informalized
has has an aspect of stress programming
that kind of
is assumed or
from my way out
awesome
question
um blue or franz what do you think
um i i don't think you're off it's this
there's definitely of course you know
that there's explicit uh incorporations
of stress until learning but your
question i think is like is it is kind
of always simplicity there even if not
explicitly
so one one interesting kind of effect
this blue mentioned earlier that stress
you know can be interpreted as like
human perceived stress hormones but it
can also just be like perturbation from
from equilibrium from homeostasis
um and they actually do kind of this
this has been breached this has been
combined and homeostatic reinforcement
learning where they kind of implicitly
explicitly make the reward and reward
based you know reinforcement learning
about the homeostatic off point
and then stress becomes suddenly a lot
more explicit
in that sense of perturbation from from
your homostatic set point
um
in the in the active inference scheme
stress is basically just your
you could just define it basically as
your you know your overall um
difference and again like with those
fans i was talking about like how much
is your is your is your private belief
certainty changing are you minimizing
uncertainty um over time or not
um
it is it is hard
i think it's hard it's hard both to
completely
uh say stress is not involved and
without saying that
while you're just calling everything
stressed but it kind of it's really it
depends on what how you define the
stress but if you think if you go score
something like as in like you stress as
you're not right now in an energy
minimized state you're not in a an
active infant scheme or you're not in a
point in a more basic scheme
then stress is i would argue you bring
into some learning yes
because without that if they don't have
the difference to that if you don't
actually
if you don't have any drive to learn
because you're not you know you think
your everything is perfect
then it's hard to to have learning so
specifically if learning is about
with the environment and context what is
your why getting into your environment i
trying to adapt to it as i try to
learning in a sense of like adapt to it
um and find a certain equilibrium with
it
then i think stress becomes very much
explicit
and it's ubiquitous
in learning
okay i just want to add one thing that's
perfect because i always talk about the
minimum of two and i think you i think
you're absolutely right friends i think
you have to then look at stress as being
either voluntary or involuntary i think
that's the minimum of two that you have
to look at because i think if you have
voluntary stress
it's it's it's
it's measurably different than the
involuntary type
so
yeah you're right i don't think it's i
don't think we can just throw under
everything under one umbrella and make
it a monolith i think we have to
partition it right from the very get-go
and say
um all programming be it a curriculum
whatever whatever the curriculum is
that those stem cells have
that's some of it's going to be
voluntary and some of it's going to be
involuntary based on the situation that
they're they're placed in
so again i wasn't trying to pull it in
that direction but
i didn't bring up stress but i really
liked that it was brought up
so okay yeah blue blue
sorry so just um from a
neuroscience perspective
um it's interesting
like the voluntary and involuntary
stress thing is so different and i feel
like maybe daniel will remember we
discussed that at some point like when
you're exposed to a stress that like you
do to yourself on purpose like your
strength training or something like that
versus
um you know some some externally imposed
stress that you didn't volunteer for i
think that that has a difference in
affect i feel like we looked at a paper
i can't remember off the top of my head
though um but
in terms of sensory processing
it's really interesting in neuroscience
we actually adapt
right so so you can listen to like you
this is a great example like you turn on
the car radio and like you're listening
jamming out in the car for i don't know
a while 20 minutes 30 minutes and then
suddenly it doesn't seem as loud and so
you turn it up and then you're jamming
out jamming out jumping out and still it
doesn't seem as loud so you turn it up
because the same level of stimulus
produces a decreasing
sensation
um and that's true in terms of you know
visual like when you first turn on the
leg you're like oh it's so bright but
then you adapt and so in in terms of
sensory processing we have a mechanism
for adaptation um and i i wonder about
actually cells like not neurons because
this is like i'm specifically talking
about like a sensory processing way but
i wonder if cells do the same thing i
mean i guess like you know the receptor
shuts or the receptors triggered and
then it can't get activated again for
some certain amount of time so even just
receptor binding in and of itself is
like an adaptation mechanism like you
can't constantly like dump the chemical
into the receptor open the channel or
whatever like that's not
like biochemically possible
but but i wonder if
um you know
cells have some other adaptation
mechanism outside of this um like
channel opening or closing or just this
is there more than like the
mechanodynamics of the channel that um
enables cellular adaptation
um i i can think of a couple ones um but
no one expert on this but um there's
right you can think of first like on the
episode on the epigenetic level if you
basically just um
you know
recruit more histones basically have a
more tightly packed chromosome you're
gonna have less genetic expression no
matter what kind of signaling input you
get to the nucleus that's whenever i can
think of it
um another one is uh
mechanically so
the right lot most of the
i hope i'm not
over generalizing but i think most of
the you know signaling against that
receptors are sensing and then has to be
transported to the nucleus somehow to to
cause transcription that is usually
directed right that has to correct up
across cytoskeleton so if you change the
mechanical properties of status skeleton
itself
um
and uh
not again yeah i'm out of my league but
um that's something i could very well
imagine um i want to ask someone that's
my smile on that topic
um
lastly
it's if you talk in in the intercell
intercellular context then
you know um
things like uh you know what we and no
in neuronal context you have these you
know the synapses in the non-neural
context you still have gap junctions and
other complexes that basically allow
transport between cells
and those can also be modulated um by
the cell so then there you can also get
habituation and definitely no examples
where people have shown habituation
and uh even other um there's active
research on on on showing that there's
more just habituation but also actually
the learning offer of a certain pattern
as well
i think that's true
so i'm really interested in the
cytoskeleton um because a lot of you
know i mean the receptors are in the
membrane embedded in the membrane but we
don't really there's not a lot of work
that looks at like the cytoskeletal
dynamics
with respect to um like modulation of
receptor dynamics right right so like
that's a field that i think or i haven't
seen very much work um in terms of how
does this the underlying cytoskeleton
contribute to the properties of the
membrane and how a cell might be
behaving and just in terms of like you
know things having to get into the
nucleus i don't know
i'm iffy on that one um i i think and
it's just because i did very early work
like transfecting cells in a variety of
different ways and you know to get a
gene into the
into the cell to get the cell to express
the gene you have to get it through the
nucleus right how does it get into the
nucleus like nobody can answer you
so like if it doesn't have a nuclear
target on it like how is it going so is
it just like osmosing itself through or
or like like just how is that exactly
happening and so you call the vendor
like oh i'm trying to use your product
whether you're electroporating or you
know using some kind of lipid mediated
transduction they don't know they have
no idea actually so it's just a super
interesting um prospect and i think that
in terms of both that and the
cytoskeleton there's a lot of like
dynamic remodeling that occurs during
cell cycles right like during the phases
you know like when a cell is dividing
and growing and becoming two cells uh um
there's and so like the nuclear membrane
that's the point
but in terms of terminally
differentiated cells like a neuron or
something that's not undergoing you know
constant change in remodeling
it's curious to see how that can happen
um and i'm interested if anybody has any
any good like hardcore mechanistic
papers that you want to point out to me
or or if anybody listening in the live
stream wants to drop them in the youtube
chat i would really love to take a look
at them
hill
i really like dean returning to this uh
idea that there's the
there's a continuum or there's multiple
archetype dimensions so not that it's
all going to map on to just two but we
know it's at least locally going to be
at minimum two
that there's the kind of
uh one mode of
interacting
in an educational or training setting
with a teaching and a taught
that could still be in an interactionist
or an instructionist
way
versus the unteaching and the untaught
so that's
the the difference between the athlete
having their form like observed in a
tight feedback versus when they're on a
social away from that sort of a training
context
and so there's like
an environment or there's a setting
where there's some kind of
stress as fundamental
and then there's another
type of environment where the different
kind of stress is fundamental
and then um franz it was an awesome
point
moving from that basic homeostatic
framing
where stress is usually considered at
the first derivative or the state so
it's like
for a thermo-organism
thermal stress is going to be when it's
hot or cold
and then that's going to be like a bowl
or it's a v or it's a bathtub or it's
some other thermal stress curve it's
about temperature
moving into the generalized coordinates
of motion with temperature
and change of temperature and change of
change in temperatures all the higher
derivatives of temperature
that expands the space a lot because
maybe it's possible that a temperature
that you slowly reach like over
10 years
is a different amount of stress than
just jumping there instantly time
matters and so the rates of change
captures that time dependence
in an instance with a snapshot vector
so that's sort of the formal use of how
we can
look beyond just the stress on
temperature
and then we introduce the whole
cognitive stress because he said well
for the active inference entity
this is sort of like the first
resonance and this is the one whose
violation of integrity results in
physical death
but then stress
moves to higher or different
analogous settings
and that could be how fast am i learning
and as pointed out by dave in the chat
and by dean and others like it really
matters whether somebody has agency
or affordances to change it and so my
closing point there with the voluntary
involuntary is like
grad school and stress
because or any
research or any educational environment
but one that many people experience is
like it can be stressful
it's also a very often privileged
setting to be in
and one is taken care of
sometimes in a way that even like
neighbors won't be and so that is
something that like i
saw first and second hand
and just thinking about the stress it's
like why is it stressful
to just read a few papers some days
or something like that
so just kind of interesting with what is
voluntary and involuntary
how we commit ourselves to different
kinds of stress of what kind it's like
well i wanted it to be novel but not
that novel
and how we actually
make those action selections
in uncertain environments
blue
so just to add on to the voluntary
versus involuntary like grad school is
an entirely voluntary endeavor obviously
but like high school is not and like i
dropped out of high school at 16. like
as soon as i was old enough to drop out
i was like i'm out like i'm not doing
this compulsory regimented program like
sorry
um no regrets right like i started
college obviously have a phd like did
well but it's the difference versus
involuntary versus voluntary like when
it's in when it's compulsory it becomes
torture like
i mean
just my just my two sets
computational group recently about um
you know the the
this whole idea of like how do you
quantify any kind of agency and
uh
josh bonga in that in that context works
with us brought up this idea instead of
talking about agency which is hard to
quantify you can talk about empowerment
and in the computational sense
empowerment is about
how much do your actions how much can
your actions influence your sensations
um again this makes um very very clear
in an active infant scheme right where
you have this markov blanket
um so like to to support example right
if you
if you don't there's no actions you can
take to change it that's
you know we can think about it as
natively stressful but we can also we
can also
define that fairly clearly in a
computational sense using something like
empowerment
so it's it's uh
and that again i like that you brought
this up because this dries home the
point that a lot of these fundamental
things you understand about stress and
human contact anyone that's ever dealt
with depression or people that suffer
from depression right knows that it's
never really about the the the
objective
total amount of stress about about how
it's being perceived by that person and
i think this empowerment helps a lot
this definition empowerment helps a lot
to understand that better how much
control do you have of that there's
other things that of course feed into
that
but it also makes them fairly clearly
that the same a lot of the fundamental
principles
must hold true and in lower organisms as
well because these definitions are of
course you know as soon as you
prescribe actions of course you can
argue that there's no real actions and
and
cell biology um then that's okay that's
just then don't want to talk about that
level but if you do look at
active states in this other context then
you do get
then you can fairly simply in an active
inference screen but other ones as well
define empowerment measure empowerment
over time by looking at how much how
much how actions actually change the
sensory states of the of the cell and
then definitions of stress from that
point of view all it's become fairly
fairly
explicit
can i ask you a question
yeah i can ask you a question because
you mentioned in the when you were with
us in the point one for a bit there
and i don't know if you re-mentioned it
today he said
you went to
mark i think and you said i want to do
something cool
we're going to bring this back to the
voluntary and involuntary piece and then
he and then you i think you said i think
you said i'd never heard of active
inference before
i was pointed in that direction
carl's lab
so
in the in the in the
context of what's voluntary and
involuntary when you when you
when you said i want to do something
cool that sounds like you wanted to do
something voluntarily
then you got then you got this deep dive
into acting
you push that up against your biology
background which is something that
you've obviously done
because you like it right and you wanted
to finish off so
so going forward now
that
that voluntary piece that got you into
the active inference what do you see the
active inference doing in terms of this
empowerment question
because daniel's written it out here
with a question mark behind it so how do
you feel
more agent a gentle agential
sorry i always kill words because i'm
not very
anyway i'm just curious what you think
now in terms of what sort of
empowerments you've
sort of
um become
in the in the sense that now that you've
got this
sense of what active inference can do
and what some of these math formalisms
provide and what this statistical
uh world
bridges yeah what do you what do you
what do you like what are you thinking
going forward in terms of the
reapplication of what you
what you pulled out of a out of a out of
a different different bucket and and and
then it's set down in the bucket that
you're most familiar with so you mean
like what where i put that on a personal
level like for my life decisions yeah
like when you're when you're going to be
going forward and trying to and trying
to use that active inference
sense yeah in terms of some of those
decisions
and what kind of environments do you
think you see yourself projecting
yourself
into that you may not have projected
yourself into
prior to
sort of engaging or encountering or
exposing yourself to activation yes
that's a question um
i think in the end
it's uh my wife and i we both love this
world where it's
serendipity and we're just excited about
happy accidents which there's all kinds
of connotations there but an active
infant scheme
or any any you know when you look at you
know what what is information for from
you
what the idea is that you
if you have too much if you have so it's
going really active inference right now
i'm starting that if you have super high
precision very strong prior beliefs
then whatever you if you are confining
yourself and you don't allow variances
um to change your mind then then you're
almost always going to be upset because
you never you know your position is set
too high right this is
there's a paper going to be coming out
soon about this collaborator as well
looks the right precision in this
context as well
so that's something that you know any
active inference model will know that
you have to you know
keep that in mind
your precisions
for me personally um
it it really is an idea of like i think
every interest this is not not novel
idea by myself but i need to stretch but
any any human
tells stories about the environment but
most about themselves and the
storytelling is in my sense nothing else
than doing a model an active influence
scheme making a generative model and
setting that so
i think too for me to
i'm way too young to be giving life
advice but
for me to to to achieve any kind of
happiness you have to really be careful
of uh
what story you tell about yourself and
how
strictly you can find that on things and
that is definitely advantage yourself
i think personally i've always had
better luck personally i think by by not
not letting not define that too too
strictly and really looking into what
what your environment throws at you and
i think that helps and i i know
personally people that have a very hard
time with that
and that have very strong model stuff
you know i'm gonna you know get married
at that age and then do this and that
and then when things don't happen that
way
i think it at least it's a lot of
unhappiness
so if
you know
in that context active influence what
can i do for you i mean
i think it's it it makes things explicit
that we all kind of hear about some
level and and you know i know when you
confirm psychology but also just you
know folk psychology things just people
giving you advice
parents saying i think oh now this is i
don't want to say that you need i have
images of any of those insights i think
you can get this lots of ways but what i
like about that inference scheme that it
you know it's it's putting this
dimension it makes makes the it makes
the thing also biology the biggest
advantages you get a very explicit
uh structure about the information flow
for very simple systems
and because it's been
primarily applied in neurosciences you
get in for us intuitive results from
that what happens if you have track
precision what happens if you probably
don't change what happens if you know if
your energy is being minimized all these
things
i can fairly easily explain that in the
context of
of of human behavior because
on lesbian's plight we all have to
understanding
um but i think there's um
for the biology point of view there's
there's a lot of things we can learn
from that if you look at the fun the
mathematical definitions
then of course it deals with the baggage
that you get from the neuroscience which
you have to deal a lot with which is
fair
um but for your life i think it just
helps you once you see really how how
much study has been put into
miss
inference you know amount like bad
inferences
um and of course people doing tests and
with
scheme about you know psychological like
behavioral task
states um then i think that that's one
lesson
i can definitely learn from that if i
hadn't already
is that being be mindful of
be mindful of your priors be mindful of
the rate of change like how what are you
really stressed out about right now
what's the worst uncertainty coming from
how much
should that throw you off right and this
is
in a sense
to kind of bring all this home a little
bit um the the biggest limitation of of
any algorithm of any model is that you
are defining the general model
beforehand
not just an active inference scheme but
any there's papers that come out that
you know criticize the idea of
artificial generalized intelligence
because you always have
predefined model and life on that sense
but that definition is
does not do that like always uh you know
biological systems evolution kind of
generates a bunch of diversity
in its background and from that
kind of um they pick the best path
constantly evolve the generative model
so you know that's kind of like
limitation of active any other algorithm
which can be overcome by you know chain
different uh objects together by
evolving system but having models make
models there's some cool work on that
too but that's something you need to
take i think
both computationally scientifically but
personally take a mind off like at what
point you change your own model and
allow for flexibility that's what makes
human right now
still that's one of the soft acts that
makes humans superior i would say into
any
um
to any kind of algorithm right now
it's because they all come predefined
with life the heart molecule which again
it's i don't really actually i'm saying
this now and also don't actually agree
with that 100
i don't actually believe in fundamental
differences between different
intelligences but that's something that
at least uh kind of intuitively makes
sense to us whether or not that's really
true scientifically i have my my points
that but that's going off off the rails
awesome wow
a few
things like we often talk about
concordances with different systems
and it brings the cognitive apparatus
that was developed for
humans
and starts to
at least instrumentally if not
from a realism perspective also project
that
and so it allows um as a trans
discipline
people to
talk about
systems and map their analogies and
models
in a way that would help us find the
resonances between
cellular metabolism and economics kind
of taking a vague feeling like those
might have some similarities
into using the same notation terms forms
etc so that's one very interesting piece
about active inference and also the
limitations
in terms of at what order
and how much
time and attention is allocated to this
structural aspect
and how many different families of
structures are provided
on one and then to your um
[Music]
well-communicated uncertainty about if
and how
biology is different from other
kinds of
processes
[Music]
that's an awesome
question especially connecting back to
your point about the reservoir of energy
versus how locally there can be a
different energy or entropy balance
so
it's almost like
there might be
little pieces
that can be mapped
to digital signal processing with super
high fidelity
and that'll be taken as like a win for
the realists
and then there might be other parts
where the instrumentalism
bridges
because we're just making a model of
this one
smaller thing and this one larger thing
and then in cases where this is fully
computationally defined
or fully described then there's like a
case
for a real what does empowerment look
like at
maybe like a low organismal level or
even like a cellular level how um
like is cellular behavior
or lower organism behavior like
voluntary versus compulsory and like is
there a way to measure
that like obviously like you can trap an
animal in a box and frequently like you
know we'll frantically try to get out
but
if you don't try it would it go into the
box and hang out there like like does
that happen maybe i don't know does
anybody know of any examples of like
what um empowerment looks like at like
that's just it's a super interesting
concept to me
um in the in the settings it's if you
take that definition off um either
conditional parts your actions change
your sensory personal perceptions
then and definitely yeah
definitely you i would i will it's if
once you have a definition it's of
course built on what your diff
actions are and that that is fairly easy
and because you don't have to go into
this route
whether it's a volunteer or not you just
base
something internal state you're
basically just even even limper you look
at the the flow of states your markup
blanket which you can show forms
naturally which car is shown
then from that point of view once you
have active states then you can measure
that fairly fairly easily so
as an example i would argue if you know
if cells actually
interact with each other and really
change other cell types we have here's a
great example
genesis is traditionally
not yeah i think it's pretty fairly
established it's really driven by life's
organizings and it's always a subsequent
of cells that will drive this cell the
ones i would argue then that those cells
are probably very much empowered because
their actions uh cause differentiation
of cells around them which then will
very much and they're going to do a
certain expression of
well so then that will they actually
very much control that whereas those
themselves um yeah they're receiving and
have a lower power because
their
their own signaling probably isn't
really because they're not not
they often just don't have that that
they don't make a lot of that signaling
celta that
it's being organized in ireland so they
are not going to have a low end
let's think of that
you're asking me what anyone yeah what
as as our guest or anyone else is
welcome to
where there to go i i pressed some light
to get to
where the thumbs more than kind of uh
qualitative like to make making actual
like instead of just like making these
abstract models of of active inference
uh you know we can measure another hand
if you can really map those two together
right like in the sense that i mean a
lot of work went into this whole spm
software that they developed and uh in
london and at this point right you
actually can get fmri data and then you
can do dynamic calls and model and you
can really
you can really postulate different
causal models and then do a you know a
bayesian belief updating you can do a
hypothesis testing right in this in the
sense that which hypothesis is more
probable to have cost
that you see
um if we get to that level on a
morphogens for example you can get the
high fidelity images of the developing
embryo that you would get
with over time get signals that you can
measure and feed back into your model
and really
make you detect the past
of what cause a model like what
structure would have caused these
sensations that you or the the data that
you're receiving that would be a huge
step forward and uh microscopy is really
doing some uh having some great advance
on that one example i can give us a
friend of mine works on that dimitri
crum and
he's been heidelberg and he would this
light sheet microscopes there's a lot of
other groups i mean he's a master
student phd student
um i bought all that from him but
there's groups um you can
do a high fidelity um light sheet from
two sides we can really nice like near
confocal resolution um but with high
high temporal resolution
um of their organism doing
and recapture the entire process of of
you know from castillation further on
last
that you could collect where you can
read and start to make
plastic causing molds in an active
inference framework and then they
basically request whereas the art
poem there
and you can really test and uh this this
the idea that we already have as
incentives i mentioned in morphogenesis
and we test out how much that that fits
into our notions of of com
no uh delete updating and actions
um that would i would love to see that
in my lifetime
wow
super awesome so just to kind of restate
that um
spm
has
been developed in the capacity of
behavioral neural imaging
and so it allows a combination of
observable features
such as like what button somebody
pressed or what image somebody was shown
and also observable features of the
environment like the measurements coming
in off of the eeg or the fmri or the meg
and it allows integrated modeling of
those different kinds of parameters
along with the dynamical causal modeling
on the underlying dynamic system
identification and there's a lot more in
the spm documentation on that
and so
active
here
along with some advances in for example
the ability to look at the process of
embryogenesis and tract cellular
location for a whole organism developing
through time
then that can be fit as if those are the
fmri measurements
of this
embryo spm
and then the underlying mechanics of
development
like a hypothesized morphogen gradient
or
a known or hypothesized mechanical
relationship
that's part of
the model that's like the underlying
neural systems model in spm
and so it's kind of
a great
dream
but if it can be stated
if it's likely to exist it sounds like
you're taking some actions that will
reduce your surprise about it
yeah pretty cool
so
on the microscopy note i'm like getting
ready to um
receive and set up
a bio afm i'm really looking forward to
like the multi-parameter
capability of like i can look structures
top a lot also like do fluorescence
imaging so i'm really excited to have
multiple affordances available on this
same
like the mic dances are great like i've
used an afm and you know it gives you
the
mechanics of your sample but
not not
it's i've never also been able to look
at the sample you just the
mapping without being able to see it so
i'm really excited to be able to see and
measure mechanic what's going on in a
cell but that's
cytoskeleton um
parameters
i was discussing earlier about how that
you know manipulates or enables cells to
do different things
cool
let's look at any other
things um or
also we can sort of give a
closing round whatever people feel like
so one one thing i'd like to find
the fight it's really about um the
aberrant signaling figure so i don't
think we went into figure five very much
last time in the dot one
and maybe
uh you could talk about the aberrant's
selling rescue kind of unpack that for
us in your own words we're not seeing
the slides anymore also daniel i don't
know if you know that
well i'm not yeah it's also kind of
lagged on youtube so i'm recording it
i'll re-upload like the high quality one
it's kind of like weird it's a normal
video chat but the youtube stream link
is like disrupted but say lovey
um yeah so
actually if you don't see the
i'm showing figure five even though you
can't see it so just
oh yeah or i see okay
we can do that
yes great thank you
awesome yes for the
voice
so this is the the top row here's the
normal simulation this reference right
you start off with these eight cells in
the beginning and then kind of have you
know this vague
uh they're very specified very low prior
belief of what type they are as they
kind of move out that
density changes so the the hue tone here
makes them means that they're now more
the more better they are the more sure
they are being this head type type cell
um
or in case of the green that the t
and b where i base
one
one cell which you can see kind of
heating off and the error points towards
that had a reduced
sensitivity
to
um two six
basically
had a really hard time
basically um first of all you know it
was much more it was longer kind of
unspecified than its neighbor balls were
and in the end it achieves actually it
gets wrong cell typewriters
not only is it a wrong position like
there's no cell
in the original one at that play
and even were you expected to be either
yellow or red or somewhere in between
but not blue as it is down here
so um
in the sense the intention of of a cell
of the cancer
is
i turn this that way because i think
that's basically the first step in
concentration is a
misidentification of your environment
and your your place in it all right the
original paper from carlos called
knowing knowing one's place the cell
definitely does not know its place so
this is what goes in and then here is
where you have basically um the same as
above but
the overall
not just the absolute flow of actually
signaling it's like two one cells is to
get to that has been up regulated so
that each cell basin now drives more
concentrations of cells to that cell and
basically kind of tries the ideas to
compensate for that
the healthy
and what happened
which i didn't expect at all
is that you have
um if you're circulating with it more
here so you don't see that so much yet
you see the cell that kind of initially
would have normally gone gone down
small cell
actually pushed
out in the end
yeah what happened
the words is that those were put into
most
io off
of
of signaling concentration
and loud arrangement
allowed this
cell to re-take a place that um
is confirmed what you say in the type of
mythology
and what i also like to i
always wait when i when i talk about
this figure and um both figures really
is
you did not in the simulation at any
point in time change topic morphology
all the actual encoding was exactly the
same
so what they're expecting where they're
expecting is exactly the same
and that i think is where i see the
fundamental
to change the code right we we know that
we have higher highest we haven't met
now energy and fire we ever had and yet
i think anyone really thinks that this
is
the way
forward in all cases and an only you
know if if you can do it and you really
come to understanding that's great and
you have no other options in an extreme
case that is absolutely unwarranted i'm
not trying to dissuade anyone anyone
from advances in gene therapy
but i think it's we you know there's the
genome is so complex so many things that
can go wrong we don't know all of the
details
that if you did not have to start
messing up people loading
that would be preferred and i think this
is all and also
from uh even just from a capability
setting you know that you don't always
have the capability not with high
fidelity that you that we think often do
so with our lab as well i
kind of take at the core of my
experimental approach to things is that
i want to understand how how cells
interact with their environment
and organs
and work on that manipulation basically
control information and sensing and
drive them towards different states
again with that arlington
and scale
that we talked last time about you want
to direct the floor do actually this
time have
i took my shirt i don't even see that
right now i do have to want landscape
there on my shirt
this time
um so that's kind of like what
because you're trying to redirect the
flow of telephate um decision making not
try to manipulate the actual ambassadors
themselves
so what was the
verb signal
response oh sorry
oh god blue there yeah the preserved
signal response so what was what was
that
yeah what was how did you perturb the
like did you cut it off did it get less
information or did it like
was it supposed to like infer an
incorrect place like how exactly in that
one cell did you manipulate the
parameters of that one cell so that it
went to a different place
yeah basically um
let me see i think
uh it was basically done on the
and uh
it was a
decrease in sensitivity is that what it
was i'm trying to make the specific
vision right now instead of hand waving
the
so let's see in the beginning that we
also formerly injuries right so that
that's basically the the how how much of
a
right this the
how much actions are being updated based
on sensory inputs
um
and we can we can put a gradient on
there and decide on that of how much
they act on that that is the part and
that i manipulate here so but that
basically means is that
by
altering the response capability of the
cell how much how much sensory update up
how many how much
to what extent
solutions are being updated based on
external information flow
and with what kind of uh you know power
on top of that
that by that you're basically upping or
reducing the sensitivity to the
environment you basically
you misarrange you misregulating the
again the compound essentially but
that's that's downstream but you know
you might be the potential of the cell
to act as environments and do anything
about
and also even upstream how much sensing
of that so in this case specifically it
just wasn't really sensing as much of
its environment as it was supposed to be
since
um it almost
is equivalent to
uh
the argument or the dissolution of sort
of nature and nurture partitioning by
just taking a complexity stance kind of
like evelyn fox keller in her book the
mirage of a space between nature and
nurture
you were talking about a target
morphology but then about how changes in
the signal were about to
do number 40
on the quantum fep paper
and blue and our friend jason and i have
been preparing a lot for it and i think
separating quantum from
the electrons and their behavior
and just asking well what is quantum
strategy
or what does this quantum statistics or
quantum information
projected onto biology mean
not how it's been approached from the
mechanistic question which is quantum
biology well that's about the synapses
and their quantum
mechanical properties
or
about
photon tunneling or proton tunneling and
like quantum effects
but what about just using the statistics
instrumentally of quantum
and talking about situations with with
complex patterns of uncertainty
and observation bias and memory and
modeling and all of that
and this was like a dot two that kind of
like
opened up a whole new area for us in our
discussions with morphology and like the
spatial and the embedded
and and then cracked a window
into just
another area we'll go into
and you brought so many awesome
insights so we really appreciate it
yeah that talk should be a real pleasure
i highly recommend
tuning in
chris fields is great too to listen to
and it's uh some exciting work and um if
you also if you have seen i'm sure you
have seen that um the the particular
paper from carl fristman he has a
section there on quantum mechanics and
it's uh it's a very cool section because
he actually um derives i think the
schrodinger occasion equation from
from a essentially from actual inference
point of view um from just a definition
of what your log probability density is
um very cool kind of uh you know and i
don't know how much um that will fit
into other and future work but the
it's it's always very exciting to me
when you see different fields at least
formally being able to be related to
each other um that usually means that
something something going on i thought
it's something fundamental
we'll have more to say
in dot 4
so and join us
yeah and of course you're welcome any
time to participate
yeah carl and i think mike i think
everybody is coming so if you want to
come and sure
join the panel you're more than pleasant
all right to the events and pop in if it
works so
thanks again everybody um hope that the
viewers can
bear with a lag if it was there but um
so peace out everyone thanks a lot for
this great discussion
thanks for having me bye
bye
you